<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and perfect relation of that most horrid &amp; hellish conspiracy of the gunpowder treason Discovered the 5th of November, anno Dom. 1605. Collected out of the best and most authentique writers, and now re-published. For further information, and to remember the people of England of Gods vvonderfull mercies and deliverances vouchsafed them, for his great name, and for his churches sake, in the defence and maintenance of the Protestant religion, established in these nations. With the names of those traytors that suffered for that bloody plot. By J.H. Gent.</title>
            <author>J. H., Gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A45628</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H82C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215848</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827610</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827610</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32032</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A45628)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32032)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1849:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and perfect relation of that most horrid &amp; hellish conspiracy of the gunpowder treason Discovered the 5th of November, anno Dom. 1605. Collected out of the best and most authentique writers, and now re-published. For further information, and to remember the people of England of Gods vvonderfull mercies and deliverances vouchsafed them, for his great name, and for his churches sake, in the defence and maintenance of the Protestant religion, established in these nations. With the names of those traytors that suffered for that bloody plot. By J.H. Gent.</title>
                  <author>J. H., Gent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Fr. Coles at the sign of the Lamb in the Old-Baily,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gunpowder Plot, 1605 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32032:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32032:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A True and Perfect RELATION OF THAT Moſt <hi>Horrid</hi> &amp; <hi>Helliſh Conſpiracy</hi> OF THE GUNPOWDER TREASON. Diſcovered the 5th. of <hi>November, Anno Dom.</hi> 1605. Collected out of the Beſt and moſt Authentique Writers, and now Re-publiſhed. For fuller information, and to remember the People of <hi>England</hi> of Gods VVonderfull Mercies and Deliverances Vouchſafed them, for his great Name, and for his Churches ſake, in the Defence and Maintenance of the Proteſtant Religion, Eſtabliſhed in theſe Nations. With the Names of thoſe <hi>Traytors</hi> that ſuffered for that <hi>bloody</hi> Plot.</p>
            <p>By <hi>I. H.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Who is like unto thee, O Lord, thou alone doſt marvellous things? The ſnare is broken, and we are eſcaped.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Fr. Coles</hi> at the Sign of the Lamb in the <hi>Old-Baily.</hi> 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:32032:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32032:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A True and Perfect Relation OF THE GUNPOWDER TREASON.</head>
            <p>THere is no Nation under Heaven, who have received and enjoyed ſo many bleſſing, both of right and left hand, as the people of <hi>England;</hi> we have had ſure preventing mercies in times paſt, and we have been honoured and ſaved by reſtoring mercies, as our late experience can ſufficiently manifeſt. God hath had more reſpect to this Age of the Church, making good all his promiſes of love and kindneſſe to it, then to all the ſeveral ages before. He hath not dealt ſo with the people round about us, nor in the Times before us<hi>: Wonderfull is his Name, and greatly to be praiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to Comply with the Time, and Solemne occaſion of our thanksgiving; ſetting aſide and waving the repetition of all other manifold Deliverances, our purpoſe is briefly here to bring to our Remembrance, and ſet before our eyes thoſe ſtrange and miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous merciful diſpenſations of the Divine Majeſty to us and our Fore-Fathers, in the revealing, diſcovering, and preventing that moſt monſtrous &amp; before unheard of miſchief, the Plot of the <hi>Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder-Treaſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In order whereunto it will be requiſite to conſider the State of the Kingdome, deducing it from the end of the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of ever Bleſſed Memory<hi>:</hi> who by the Divine providence eſcaped not a few dangerous conſpiracies againſt her Life, and conſequently againſt the ſafety of the Church and Kingdom; All theſe wicked Machavilians Deſignes were principally laid, fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32032:3"/>
and abetted, and intented to be executed by <hi>Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques,</hi> incited thereunto by the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and other Emiſſaries of the Pope and See of <hi>Rome.</hi> For which reaſon divers Statutes were made by Parliament (for the better ſecurity of her Perſon and Government) againſt Prieſts and Seminaries and ſuch as ſhould be reconciled, that was, perverted to the Romiſh Religion; and for breach of thoſe ſtatutes, enjoyning thoſe Prieſts departure and abſence out of the Kingdome, and for other Offences ſeveral of them were Executed, to the great Exulceration and Exaſperation of the reſt of that Perſwaſion and Religion, who could by no means endure that Queen or her Government.</p>
            <p>She dying, the Papiſts of <hi>England</hi> were in great hopes that her Succeſſour King <hi>James</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whoſe Mother in their Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion dyed a Martyr for their Religion, in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> would not only remit and ſurceaſe thoſe rigours they had before ſuffered, but would alſo grant them free Exerciſe and Toleration of their Religion, and grew very confident and jolly in this vain expectation<hi>:</hi> which when they perceived to be fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated and diſappointed, at that Kings very firſt coming in and aſſumption to this Crown, by his declaring his conſtant reſolution for the maintenance of the Religion here Eſtabliſhed; a conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy was entred into by one <hi>Watſon</hi> and <hi>Clarke,</hi> Prieſts, the Lord <hi>Cobham</hi> and <hi>George Brooke</hi> his Brother, <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord <hi>Gray</hi> of <hi>Wilton,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Rawleih,</hi> Sir <hi>Griffin Markham,</hi> Sir <hi>Edward Parham, Bartholomew Brookesby</hi> and <hi>Anthony Coply:</hi> their deſign being to ſurprize the King and Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> and ſecuring of them, either at the <hi>Tower</hi> or <hi>Dover,</hi> there by violence to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their own pardons, a Tolleration of Religion, and a remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val of ſome Councellours, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And to conceal this Treaſon the better, <hi>Watſon</hi> deviſed Oaths of ſecreſie, teaching that the Act was lawful being done before the Coronation, (for the King had deferr'd that Solemnity till St. <hi>Jamſe's</hi> day, a while after) becauſe the King was no King before he was anointed and the Crown So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly ſet on His Head.</p>
            <p>This Plot came by the Wiſe Providence of God to be diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the conſpirators tryed for it at <hi>Wincheſter;</hi> the Term be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing adjourned thither, becauſe of the Plague then in <hi>London,</hi> where they were all Condemned but onely three of them, <hi>viz. George Brooke</hi> 
               <abbr>Esq</abbr> 
               <hi>Watſon</hi> and <hi>Clerke</hi> Prieſts; three other, <hi>viz.</hi> the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32032:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Lords, <hi>Cobham</hi> and <hi>Gray,</hi> and Sir <hi>Griffin Markham</hi> were brought upon the Scaffold, and by the Kings Grace and Mercy ſeverally Reprieved, Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh,</hi> that famous Hiſtorian, many years after was charged with the ſame Judgement, and Beheaded in <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Palace Yard.</p>
            <p>This end had theſe Troublers of the State, whoſe Grand Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, ſuch as the Politick Civil Lord <hi>Burleigh,</hi> were too wary and jealous to be ſurprized by ſuch Devices; and the Nation now ſeemed to be in a moſt ſweet and laſting peace, through the wiſe temperament of the King and his more indulgent hand, the then Papiſts for many years had felt; when loe a moſt Deſperate and Infernal Conjuration was laid, by ſome Grandees and mad Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots of that Religion; a Plot ſo impiouſly wicked, that the former was a meer ſhadow to this intended blaze and conflagration: the very recital whereof makes the Pen to <hi>Tremble</hi> with the thought of thoſe <hi>ſhakings, revulſions,</hi> and <hi>trepidations</hi> this dire Blow would have Cauſed.</p>
            <p>This Horrid Treaſon was firſt thought on in the laſt year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth; Thomas Winter</hi> being ſent into <hi>Spain</hi> by other his Complices, to deſire that King in the name of the Engliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiques, to ſend an Army into <hi>England,</hi> with whom they and the Male-contented Gentry and Souldiery at the Earle of <hi>Eſſexe's</hi> death would be ready to joine<hi>:</hi> which being aſſented to, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and agreed on by the ſaid King, <hi>Winter</hi> returned into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and gave a welcome account to his party and Negotiation; but Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> dying, though they would have perſwaded the <hi>Spaniard</hi> to bold his former Reſolution, yet he now would not further hearken to any ſuch motion.</p>
            <p>In the mean while the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> had been tampering to diſwade the acceptance of King <hi>James</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> urging it, that death was rather to be endured then to admit a Heretique; from which principle &amp; other the like ſtuffe out of <hi>Parſons</hi> his book, <hi>Philopater Sect.</hi> 1. <hi>Catesby</hi> the firſt in the Conſpiracy, took his ground, <hi>it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the then</hi> Juſuits <hi>poſition: That if any Chriſtian Prince ſhall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifestly turn from the Catholique Religion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he preſently falleth from all Princely Power and Dignity, and that</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>before any ſentence pronounced againſt him by the ſupreame Judge and Paſtour; and that his Subjects are Abſolved from all Bonds and Oaths of Allegiance,</hi> &amp;c. By ſuch like fiery Divinity of their own making the Gunpowder-Treaſon took ſtrength.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:32032:4"/>
The Parliament then called by the King, was Prorogued from the 7th. of <hi>July,</hi> to the 7th. of <hi>February:</hi> a little before which Prorogation, <hi>Catesby</hi> then at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> ſent for <hi>Thomas Winter</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and broke with him concerning this Powder-plot<hi>:</hi> who anſwered, that indeed ſtruck at the root, but if it ſhould miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carry, the Catholique Cauſe would be greatly Scandalized: <hi>Catesby</hi> replyed, the nature of the Diſeaſe required ſo ſharp a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and then demanded his conſent; which he freely gave, but propoſed difficulties as want of an Houſe, the difficulty of the Myne noiſe in working, and ſuch like, which <hi>Catesby</hi> ſatisfied by telling him, let us begin the attempt, and where it ſaileth let us paſſe no further. Then they agreed that the Conſtable of <hi>Spain,</hi> then in the Low Countries ſhould be dealt withal for aſſiſtance, but not the plot to be diſcovered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> and other Fugitives ſhould be underfelt; chiefly one <hi>Guido Fawkes</hi> employed about the firſt overture to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and then in that Kingdome, ſhould be drawn to the aſſociation. Sir <hi>VVil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Stanley</hi> declined all general propoſitions that was, yet hoping to make his peace in <hi>England,</hi> but brought <hi>Fawkes</hi> to <hi>VVinters</hi> acquaintance, who dealt together with one <hi>Owen</hi> about the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Fawkes</hi> was a Gentleman of <hi>Darbiſhire,</hi> reſolute in any undertaking for his Religion: and ſo <hi>VVinter</hi> and he returned into <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Catesby,</hi> to whom came <hi>Thomas Percy,</hi> kinſman to the late Earle of <hi>Northumberland;</hi> where after a ſhort conference, they agreed upon an Oath of ſecrecy; Swearing by the Bleſſed Trinity and the Sacrament never to diſcloſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Catesby,</hi> who had drawn in one <hi>John VVright,</hi> diſcovered the plot to <hi>Percy</hi> and <hi>Winter,</hi> and <hi>Jack VVright</hi> to <hi>Fawkes;</hi> and ſo they reſolved to proceed.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe <hi>Percy</hi> was ordered to take the Houſe where to lodge inſtruments of Violence and Death, which he hired of one <hi>Ferris,</hi> who Tenanted it of Mr. <hi>Whineyard,</hi> belonging to the Wardrobe; and <hi>Fawkes</hi> by the name of <hi>John Johnſon,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi>'s man was put in to poſſeſſe it, and received the keyes of the Houſe. It was alſo thought convenient to have another Houſe to lodge the powder and proviſion for the Mine, from thence to be conveyed to Mr. <hi>Percy</hi>'s; ſo one was taken in <hi>Lambeth,</hi> and one <hi>Keyes</hi> appointed the keeper thereof. Now they fell to work upon the Mine having ſtore of baked meats with them the leſſe to need ſending abroad.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:32032:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
The chief Conſpirators were now in Conſultation what they ſhould doe when the deed was done, and agreed to ſeize upon the Duke that was our late King <hi>Charles,</hi> of bleſſed Memory, and the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (the King and Prince <hi>Henry</hi> being devoted to the Flames) and having warned others of the Popiſh Nobility to forbear ſitting in Parliament to get what number of Horſes they could; which ſtrength, having the Heir apparent with them, would be odds ſufficient, in that general confuſion and Conſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which would attend the Effects of their Treaſon.</p>
            <p>About <hi>Candlemas</hi> they brought over in a Boat the <hi>Powder</hi> which they had provided at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> and laid it in Mr. <hi>Piercy</hi> his Houſe, becauſe they would have all their danger in one Place. Then falling to their Work in the Mine, they came againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Houſe ſtone wall, which was very hard to beat through, at which time they called in <hi>Chriſtopher Wright</hi> to their Company. As they were thus labouring, they heard a ruſling noyſe, which was the removal of ſome Coals, that made them think they were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered; but <hi>Fawks</hi> being ſent thither to know the buſineſs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood the Coals were a ſelling, and that the Cellar was to be Let, which for its conveniency, <hi>Piercy</hi> preſently hired, and put into it 20 Barrels of Powder, newly provided, and covered them with Billets and Fagots, provided for the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Their Work being in ſuch a readineſſe, <hi>Fawks</hi> was ſent over into <hi>Flanders</hi> to give the <hi>Oath of Secrecy</hi> to Sir <hi>William Stanley</hi> and get him over and <hi>Owen;</hi> Sir <hi>William</hi> was in <hi>Spain, Owen</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med well pleaſed but ſaid Sir <hi>William</hi> would not engage. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Fawks</hi> returned about <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Parliament having been prorogued from the 7th of <hi>February</hi> before-going, to the 5th of <hi>November.</hi> About this time Mr. <hi>Piercy</hi> and Mr. <hi>Catesby</hi> met at the <hi>Bath,</hi> where they agreed that few being yet in the Company, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesby</hi> ſhould have Authority to call in whom he pleaſed; who drew in Sir <hi>Everard Digby,</hi> Mr. <hi>Treſham</hi> of <hi>Northampton ſhire,</hi> who contributed Money to the carrying on of the Deſign.</p>
            <p>In the interim, <hi>Fawks</hi> and <hi>Winter</hi> bought ſome new Powder, as ſuſpecting the firſt to be damp, and conveyed it into the Cellar, and then for ten dayes before the ſitting of the Parliament, went down into the Country, where by <hi>Enfield</hi> Chaſe, at a place cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Whitewebs,</hi> they communed with <hi>Catesby,</hi> who asked them if ther Pince would come to the Parliament, who replying negatively
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32032:5"/>
he ſaid then we muſt have our Horſes beyond the Water, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of more Company to ſurprize the Prince, and leave the Duke alone.</p>
            <p>All things thus laid and fitted, according to their former reſult of warning the Popiſh Lords from the danger, being ſome ten days before the ſitting down of the Parliament, a Letter was put about ſeven of the Clock on a <hi>Saturday</hi> Evening, into the hands of a Footman of the Lord <hi>Mounteagles</hi> in the Street by an unknown man of a reaſonable tall ſtature, with a Charge to deliver it to his Lords own hands, which he did; my Lord no ſooner received it, but perceiving it writ in an unlegible Hand, he commanded one of his ſervants to read it, when perplext with the ſtrangeneſs of the matter (think it might prove ſome fooliſh deviſed ſtory or other) he haſted away with it to <hi>Whitehall</hi> to the Secretary, the Earl of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> who peruſing it likewiſe, commended my Lords care and diſcretion, telling him, that whatever the Letter ſeemed, yet had he received Advertiſements from beyond Sea concerning ſome practices of the Papiſts to make new ſtirs, to the enabling them to deliver to the King a Petition for Toleration of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion like ſturdy Beggars that would force, if they could not beg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an Almes. The Earl added, that he would preſently communicate it to ſome others of the privy Council, <hi>Mounteagle</hi> onely deſiring that what ever the iſſue or meaning of it might be, it might not be imputed to him as proceeding from his too light and ſudden ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion which his Majeſties ſafety had onely prompted him to. The Lord Chamberlain was therefore made acquainted firſt with it in the preſence of the Lord <hi>Mounteagle,</hi> who likewiſe concur'd there was ſome perillous attempt intended againſt the Kings Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which the Lord Chamberlain by his Office was principally concerned to take care of as well in all publique places of Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, as in his Majeſties own private Palaces.</p>
            <p>Whereupon the ſaid Letter was by conſent communicated to three more Lords of the privy Council, the Earls of <hi>Worceſter</hi> and <hi>Northampton,</hi> and the Lord Admiral, who all concluded it was a matter not to be ſlighted, and that the King ſhould be informed thereof, that in the mean time no other noyſe ſhould be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, that the Deſign might ripen and be the fitter for Diſcovery. According to this determination, the Earl of <hi>Salisbury</hi> in the Gallery at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> on <hi>Friday</hi> being <hi>Allhallows</hi> day, delivered
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:32032:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the King the Letter, without any ſpeech or judgement made of it; the Contents whereof were as followeth.</p>
            <q>
               <p>My Lord, <hi>Out of the love I bear to ſome of your Friende, I have a care of your preſervation; Therefore I would adviſe yoa as you ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your ſafety to deviſe ſome Excuſe to ſhift off your Attendance at this Parliament; for God and Man have decreed to puniſh the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs of this time. And think not ſlightly of this Advertiſement, but retire your ſelf into your County, where you may expect the Event in ſafety; for though there be no appearance of any ſtir, yet I ſay, they ſhall receive a terrible blow this Parliament, and yet they ſhall not ſee who hurt them. This Counſel is not to be contemned, becauſe it may do you good, and can do you no harm, for the danger is paſt as ſoon as you have burned this Letter; And I hope God will give you grace to make good uſe of it, to whoſe Holy Protection I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>The King (who was alwaies very fortunate in ſolving of <hi>Ridles)</hi> ne ſooner read the Letter, but after a little pauſe, and the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it over again, he delivered his judgement of it as of a matter not to be ſlighted; for that the ſtile of it was not like a Paſquil: when the Earl of <hi>Salisbury</hi> perceiving the King to apprehend it deeplier then he expected, hinted to the <hi>King</hi> that by one clauſe thereof <hi>(that the danger was paſt as ſoon as the Letter was burned)</hi> it ſeemed to be written by a fool or mad man; for what would the notice of the danger advantage or availe any man, when the burning of the Letter was ſufficient to avoid it? But the <hi>King</hi> joyning and referring that clauſe to another (that they ſhould receive a terrible blow that Parliament) did happily gueſs that the danger intended there was by ſome ſudden blowing up of powder; for no other Rebellion or Inſurrection whatſoever, could be attempted unſeen in time of Parliament, but by that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, nor no miſchief take effect but that ſpeedy way of deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; &amp; to that ſenſe he rightly turned and conſtrued (the danger is paſt <hi>as ſoon)</hi> to that of <hi>as quickly;</hi> and therefore adviſed that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his going to Parliament the under-rooms of the Parliament Houſe might be well and narrowly ſearched. It muſt be confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſed that God put this interpretation into the <hi>Kings</hi> Heart; for though now upon the event appearing, no other conſtruction can be made of the letter, yet before, the wiſeſt did not apprehend that meaning<hi>:</hi> ſo that next to God the Nation is beholding to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:32032:6"/>
King their Head, for this his temporal ſaving knowledge.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Salisbury</hi> wond'ring at this ſtrange, yet rationall Commentary of the King, which he knew to be farre contrary to his ordinary and natural diſpoſition that was alwaies averſe from or editing due advertiſements of practiſes againſt his perſon; and rightly conceiving this extraordinary caution of having the rooms ſearched, proceeded from the Vigilant care he had of the State, more then of himſelf<hi>:</hi> thought fit to diſſemble his concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent apprehenſion of the danger, putting it off with ſome jeſt or merry diſcourſe, and ſo took his leave of his Majeſty, but repai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red inſtantly to the ſame Lords of the privy Counſel<hi>:</hi> whom he acquainted with the Kings judgement, and conſtruction of the Letter, and what had elſe paſſed in private; who agreed that the ſaid Earle ſhould put his Majeſty again in mind of the buſineſſe, the next day being <hi>Saturday,</hi> when it was ordered, the Lord Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain being preſent; that the ſaid Lord Chamberlain ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Cuſtome and Office, as uſually, view both Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Houſes above and below; and ſee and conſider what like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood or poſſibility of danger might be layed there. But becauſe they would not have any rumour fly abroad, and alſo for the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler diſcovery of the plot, if there were really ſuch a thing; it was reſolved that he ſhould not go thither while <hi>Munday</hi> in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon, the day before the ſetting down of the Parliament<hi>:</hi> at which time he went thither, accompanied with the Lord <hi>Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eagle,</hi> who impatiently expected the event; Being there, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving reviewed all the lower rooms, he found in the Vault, under the upper Houſe great ſtore of proviſion, of Billets, Faggots, and Coles; and enquiring of <hi>Whinyard</hi> keeper of the Wardrobe, to what uſe he had put thoſe lower Rooms and Cellers? he replyed, that Mr. <hi>Thomas Percy</hi> had hired the Houſe and part of the Vault under the ſame; and that the ſaid Wood and Coal was alſo his proviſion; whereupon the Lord <hi>Chamberlain</hi> caſting his eye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, eſpied <hi>Fawks</hi> the pretended ſervant of <hi>Percy</hi> in a corner, but took no further notice of the man.</p>
            <p>At the naming of <hi>Percy,</hi> the Lord <hi>Mounteagle</hi> began to ſuſpect the matter, and that the Letter might probably be ſent from him, and intimated afterward ſo much to my Lord <hi>Chamberlain:</hi> who among the other things he related to have ſeen and conſidered, omitted not the ſuſpition of <hi>Mounteagles,</hi> as alſo the jealouſie he
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32032:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
had of ſuch a great quantity of Coals, Faggots and Billets, for a perſons uſe that had not been, nor yet was reſident in the houſe he pretended to take for his dwelling<hi>:</hi> whereupon the King inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Houſe was to be narrowly ſearched to the bottome, it being to be ſuſpected that thoſe Faggots were laid there onely for covering of the powder, of which opinion were all the Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours preſent; but the manner of the ſearch was not ſo well agreed on, for as the Kings and Kingdomes ſafety required all Caution for preventing the danger, ſo the reputation of the State, and the imputation it would lay upon the Earle of <hi>Northumberland,</hi> whoſe Kinſman and moſt Confident Familiar this <hi>Percy</hi> was, if it ſhould prove but a Fable after a curious and ſtrict ſearch, made them loath to be too eager therein; the rather becauſe it was known how much the King deteſted to be thought jealous or ſuſpicious of any of his good Subjects. But the Kings reſolute perſiſtency for a through ſearch prevayled, for as he ſaid it could prejudice no man at all that was innocent: and either they muſt examine the bottome of the matter, that no poſſibility of danger might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, or elſe not to meddle any further in it but plainly to go next day to the Parliament, and leave the ſucceſſe to Fortune, which he believed they would hardly take upon their conſciences.</p>
            <p>It was therefore finally reſolved to ſearch all places, and upon the pretence of <hi>Whinyards</hi> miſſing ſome of the Kings goods to view thoſe rooms narrowly for them. And to this purpoſe Sir <hi>Thomas Knevet,</hi> a Gentleman of his Majeſties privy Chamber, and a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the peace in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> was employed<hi>:</hi> who according to the truſt repoſed in him, went about the midnight next after, accompanied with ſuch a ſmall number as was fit for that errand; and at his coming neer the Houſe, ſeeing <hi>Fawkes, Percy's</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded man, ſtanding without doors at that dead time of night, with his Cloaths and Boots on, he apprehended him, and then proceeded to the ſearch. In which after he had cauſed ſome of the Billets, Faggots, and Coals to be overturned; he firſt found one of the Barrels of powder, and afterwards 35 more, being 36 in all. And ſearching the fellow he had taken, he found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> matches and all other inſtruments fit for blowing up of powder <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his pockets and about him, which made him inſtantly to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his own Guiltineſs, but in ſuch a wicked manner that he ſaid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he been within the Houſe when Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> took him, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:32032:7"/>
juſt before (to the ending of his work) he would not have failed to have blown up Himſelf, Houſe and altogether, but it pleaſed God by this his opportune ſeizure to prevent every part of that Dive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Invention.</p>
            <p>After Sir <hi>Thomas</hi> had cauſed this Caitiff to be ſurely bound and well guarded, he returned to <hi>Whitehall,</hi> and gave notice to the Lord Chamberlain and Earl of <hi>Salisbury</hi> of his ſucceſs, who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently rouzed the reſt of the Council that lay in the Court, to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble together, who as they ſoon as they could get ready, came and forthwith entred the Kings Bed-chamber together, where the Lord Chamberlain could not refrain his ſudden gladneſs, but at firſt entry told the King in a confuſed haſt that all was diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and the Traytor bound and in Cuſtody.</p>
            <p>The King aroſe, and ſending for the reſt of the Council then in Town, the Priſoner was commanded to be brought in (having ſtood without ſome while to the gazing and wonderment of the people without any alteration of countenance or dejection of ſpirit) when notwithſtanding the Horrour of his Guilt, and his ſudden ſurprizal and the terrour which the preſence of ſo grave a Council muſt needs ſtrike him with, yet he continued obſtinate againſt all manner of revealing his Complices, nor could the Council get any thing of him all that day as to any diſcovery, he laying at the blame upon himſelf, ſaying he was moved thereunto onely for Religion and Conſcience ſake, denying the King to be his lawful Soveraign or the Anointed of God, in regard he was an Heretick<hi>:</hi> and the ſame regardleſs geſture and countenance he uſed before the Council, the ſame he kept all that day of his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, anſwering with ſcorn to ſuch as he knew had no power to examine him and ſmiling in their faces, nor would he be drawn to confeſs any other name then <hi>John Johnſon.</hi> But after two or three dayes conſideration in the <hi>Tower,</hi> of the certainty of his Death and the fright of the Rack which was ſhewed him only, he begun to fail in his reſolution; confeſſing part and then the whole truth<hi>:</hi> of which this is the perfect abſtract.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The principal Conſpirators and that laboured in the Mine by this Confeſſion, were</hi> Robert Catesby, Robert Winter, <hi>Eſq.</hi> Thomas Piercy, Thomas Winter, John <hi>and</hi> Chriſtopher Wright, Fawks, <hi>and</hi> Bates, Catesby<hi>'s Man. The acceſſories to it, though not perſonally la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring in the Mine, were</hi> Everard Digby, <hi>Knight,</hi> Ambroſe Roke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32032:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>and</hi> Francis Treſham, <hi>Eſquires,</hi> John Graunt, <hi>Gentleman,</hi> Robert Keyes.</p>
            <p>Upon the ſpreading of the News, on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 5. of <hi>Novemb.</hi> the Town was all over in an Extaſie and a kind of joyful uproar; the <hi>Londoners</hi> flocking down towards <hi>Westminſter,</hi> to bleſſe their eyes with thoſe ſtanding ſtructures deſigned for the Kingdoms and their own Tomb, while <hi>Winter</hi> and the two <hi>Wrights (Catesby</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing gone the night before, and <hi>Piercy</hi> at four of the clock in the morning the ſame day of the Diſcovery) haſtned out of the Town, all of them flying for <hi>VVarwick-ſhire,</hi> where about two of the clock in the morning the ſame day, <hi>Graunt,</hi> with other his aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociates, had broke up a Stable of one Mr. <hi>Benock,</hi> a Trainer of great Horſes for the Nobility and Gentry thereabouts, and carried away eight Horſes fit for ſervice, and with them met with that Company which fled out of <hi>London</hi> at <hi>Dunchurch,</hi> at Sir <hi>Everard Digby</hi> his Lodging, who had appointed a Hunting Match on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to draw his party the more unſuſpectedly together. This Helliſh Company being thus met, and finding their Treaſon diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, reſolved to run a deſperate Courſe, and from cloſe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery, run into open rebellion, thinking if more joyned with them to ſave themſelves in the throng; but this Snow-ball waſted inſtead of increaſing, and therewith the hopes of animating a party by their Example; for they had much adoe to keep their Servants from flying from them; and their whole number made but eighty, who having wandred a while through <hi>VVarwick-ſhire</hi> to <hi>VVorceſter-ſhire,</hi> and from thence to the edge and Confines of <hi>Stafford-ſhire.</hi> This Rebel Bravado had not the Honour to be beaten with a Kings Lievtenant or extraordinary Commiſſioner, but by the ordinary Sheriff of <hi>VVorceſter</hi> they were all beaten and taken. For though their ſpeedy flight prevented the Kings Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, whereby their Horrid Fact was ſet forth, yet the County without any ſuch incentive were ready to ſuppreſs them of theie own accord, knowing that armed concourſe could portend no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, then a Rebellion. Upon which gueſs, the Country refuſed to give them willingly ſo much as a Cup of Drink or any manner of comfort and ſupport, but with execrations deſerted them, and a poor Smith ſtruck at <hi>VVinter,</hi> and had ſeized him, but that he was reſcued by his party<hi>:</hi> And ſo at laſt after Sir <hi>Richard Verney</hi> High Sheriff of <hi>VVarwick-ſhire</hi> them had carefully and cloſely
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32032:8"/>
chaſed them to the Confines of his County, ſome of the meaner ſort being alſo apprehended by him, Sir <hi>Richard VValſh</hi> did like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe hotly purſue them through his Shire; And having gotten ſome tice of their taking Harbour in Mr. <hi>Littletons</hi> Houſe, he ſent Trumpeters and Meſſengers to them in the Kings Name, to render themſelves to him His Majeſties Miniſter, and knowing no more of their Crime then what was publiquely viſible, did promiſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their dutiful and obedient Rendition to him, to intercede at the Kings hands for the ſparing of their Lives, who received only from them this ſcornful Anſwer, <hi>(They being better witneſſes to themſelves of their own demerits) that he had need of better Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance then of thoſe few Numbers that were with him, before he could be able to Command or Controul them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here the wondrous work of Gods juſtice now magnified it ſelf, for while this meſſage paſſed between the Sheriffe and them, the Sheriffe and his peoples zeal being juſtly kindled and augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their arrogant anſwer; and therefore preparing to give a furious aſſault, and the other party making themſelves ready within the houſe to performe their promiſe by a defence as reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute; it pleaſed God that in the mending of the Fire in their Chamber, one ſmall ſpark ſhould flye out and light upon leſs then two pound weight of powder, which was drying a little from the Chimney; which being thereby blown up, ſo ſpoyled the faces of ſome of the prinacipal Rebels, and the hands and ſides of others of them (blowing up with it alſo another great bag of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which notwithſtanding took not fire) that they were not only diſabled and diſcouraged thereby from any further reſiſtance, in reſpect <hi>Catesby, Rookewood, Grant,</hi> and divers others of greateſt account among them, were thereby made unable of defence; but alſo wonderfully ſtrucken with amazement in their guilty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences; calling to memory how God had juſtly puniſhed them with that ſame inſtrument, which they would have uſed before for the accompliſhing ſo great a ſin, according to that ſentence, <hi>in that in which we ſin, in the ſame ſhall we be puniſhed.</hi> In ſo much as they preſently (ſee the wonderful power of Gods Juſtice upon guilty Conſciences) did all fall down upon their knees, praying God to pardon them for their bloody enterprize. And after that giving over any further debate, opened the Gate and ſuffered the Sheriffs people to ruſh in among them, of whom they deſperately
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32032:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
ſought their own deſtruction. The three principal of them, <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesby, Percy</hi> and <hi>Winter</hi> joyned backs together<hi>:</hi> whereof <hi>Catesby</hi> and <hi>Percy,</hi> (though the Proclamation directed the taking of him alone if poſſible, becauſe the whole Cabol and miſtery of the deſigne was lodged in him, by reaſon of his great Relations and acquaintance) were ſlain; <hi>VVinter</hi> was taken and ſaved alive.</p>
            <p>And thus thoſe reſolute and furious cruel Papiſts, who dreamed of no leſſe then the deſtruction of Kings and Kingdoms, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to themſelves no lower Eſtate, then the Government of great and Ancient Monarchies; were miſerably Defeated and quite overthrown in an inſtant, falling iato the pit which they had prepared for others. And ſo fulfilling that ſentence, which his Majeſty did in a manner propheſie of them in his Oration to the Parliament; ſome of them being preſently ſlain, others deadly wounded, ſtripped of their Cloaths, and left lying miſerably na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and ſo dying rather of Cold then of their Wounds; and the reſt that either were whole, or but lightly hurt, taken and led pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners to the Jayle (by the Sheriffe, the ordinary Miniſter of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to the ordinary priſon of the worſt (yet compared with theſe) harmleſſe Malefactors, where they remained till their ſending up to <hi>London,</hi> being met with a huge confluence of all ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, deſirous to ſee them as the rareſt and unuſualleſt ſort of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and as the publique ſpectacle of ſhame and Gods fieree wrath, and juſt indignation. They lived bloodily in ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they practiſed divelliſhly in all manner of impiety, and they dyed deſperately in diſgrace and ignominy<hi>: And their memory ſhall be curſed throughout all Generations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Cauſe have we then, and how many wayes are we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked to truſt in God, and to love and worſhip him, that ſo mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly hath defended us; eſpecially ſince it is to be feared, that he in his juſt diſpleaſure for our unthankfulneſſe, did give us up and our late Bleſſed Soveraigne to the unreaſonable violence of moſt ungodly and blood thirſty men; and oh that all the undu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful company who promoted that ſad Rebellion, would conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of this and our late good providence, and repent from their Hearts of the great evil they have done, leſt vengeance overtake them alſo. Let us therefore lift up our hearts to God, for he hath put a <hi>new</hi> Song of Joy and Thanksgiving into our Mouths, and mercifully taught us, <hi>to lift up our Eyes to him from when cometh</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:32032:9"/>
               <hi>our Salvation.</hi> Pſal. 121. <hi>Our help cometh from the Lord which hath made Heaven and Earth. He will not ſuffer our Feet to ſlip, for he that keepeth us will not ſlumber, for behold he that keepeth</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>will neither ſlumber nor ſleep. The Lord is our Keeper, the Lord is our Defence at our right Hand.</hi> Which God of his Infinite Mercy ſtill ſtretch out to our Protection, and continue us in Peace and Quietneſſe, from the treacherous practiſes of the Jeſuited Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, and the bold and Rebellious Outrages of Sects and Schiſme. <hi>And let all the people ſay Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN <hi>January</hi> following a Commiſſion was iſſued out to ſeverall Judges of both Benches for the Tryal of thoſe Traytors: who ſate on the 27th. of that moneth, and gave ſentence of Death up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them<hi>:</hi> and on the <hi>Thursday</hi> following, Sir <hi>Everard Digby</hi> of <hi>Gothurſt,</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks; Robert VVinter</hi> of <hi>Hodington,</hi> in the County of <hi>VVarwick; Graunt</hi> of <hi>Yarthbrook</hi> the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and <hi>Bates,</hi> were Executed at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls;</hi> on the next day, being <hi>Friday, Thomas VVinter, Keys, Ambroſe, Bookewoood</hi> of <hi>Staningfield</hi> in that County Eſquire, and <hi>Fawkes</hi> were Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted in the Palace-yard at <hi>VVeſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Everard</hi> for his good parts was pitied, the reſt were ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for themſelves. It is obſervable that in <hi>Catesby,</hi> the Name and Family of that Councellour and Privado of <hi>Richard</hi> the Third, who was alſo the betrayer of his Patron, the Lord <hi>Haſtings</hi> expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; one ſin puniſhing another in the like Guilt. <hi>Francis Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham</hi> of <hi>Northamptonſhire</hi> Eſquire, another of the Conſpirators, remained about Court and fled not, put proffered his ready ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice for the ſuppreſſion of his Fellowes, yet ſuſpected of partaking with them, he was committed to the <hi>Tower,</hi> where before their Arraignment as aforeſaid, he dyed of the <hi>Strangury; Garnet</hi> the Jeſuite, who concealed this Treaſon, was executed likewiſe in <hi>March</hi> following, who confeſſed his Fault.</p>
            <p>So ended the Unfortunate Traytors, giving us cauſe to ſay, <hi>Soli Deo gloria.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:32032:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
